check out this new video on the
microbiome and if you want more just go
to nutritionfacts.org
topics
microbiome for all my videos on good gut
health
[Music]
when we eat meat
dairy eggs
seafood
our gut flora can take certain
components in them carnitine and choline
and produce something that ends up as a
toxic compound called tmao
which may set us up for a heart attack
stroke
and death so give people two eggs and
you get a spike of tmao in your
bloodstream within hours of consumption
because gut bacteria play a critical
role in this process though if you then
give them a week of antibiotics to wipe
out their gut flora and re-feed them to
more eggs nothing happens
no tmao in their bloodstream because
they have no egg-eating bacteria to make
it
but give it a month for their gut
bacteria to start to grow back and the
eggs start to cause tmao production once
again
same thing with meat give people the
equivalent of an 11 ounce steak and tmao
levels shoot up in the blood but feed
them the same amount after a week of
antibiotics and nothing happens
so to run into problems you need both
the meat and the meat eating bugs that's
why you can feed a vegan a sirloin and
they don't produce tmao within their
body
they just don't have the meat eating
bugs in their gut okay now this should
all be old news for those who've been
following the science the reason for
this video is to show that this
phenomenon happens the other way around
too
when we eat whole plant foods like
fruits vegetables whole grains and beans
along with nuts and seeds a gut flora
can take certain components in them
fiber and resistant starch and produce
short chain fatty acids which can set us
up for the prevention of human diseases
short chain fatty acids like butyrate
can help seal up a leaky gut fight
inflammation prevent weight gain improve
insulin sensitivity accelerate weight
loss and fight cancer
but these benefits rely on two things
eating fiber and having fiber feeding
bugs just like the detrimental effects
from tmao
required not only eggs dairy or meat but
also the eggs dairy or meat munching
bugs
check this out if you give people whole
intact grains in this case barley
kernels also known as barley groats
three servings a day like i recommend in
my daily dozen app within just three
days of eating that extra 30 plus grams
of fiber and resistant starch their gut
bugs were so happy and produced so many
short chain fatty acids that people's
insulin levels improved by 25
which means their bodies needed to
produce less insulin to take care of the
same amount of white bread while still
dampening the blood sugar spike
but this was on average some people
responded to all that extra fiber with
beautiful dips in blood sugar and
insulin responses but in others the same
amount of fiber resistant starch didn't
work at all why
because you don't just need fiber but
fiber feeding bugs like prevotella
how do you get more prevoteela so you
can take full advantage of the health
benefits of plants
eat more plants privately abundance is
associated with long-term fiber intake
if you look at rural african children
eating 97 whole food plant-based diets
their prevotel is off the charts
compared to kids eating standard western
diets and this is reflected in the
amount of short-chain fatty acids
they're churning out in their poop
in the industrialized world it's those
habitually eating vegetarian and vegan
that promotes the enrichment of
fiber-eating bacteria in the gut
here's the relative prevotel abundance
between those who eat meat
no meat or all plants
this may help explain the worse
inflammatory profile in omnivores than
in vegetarians
based on the findings relative to
bacteria abundance the researchers
suggest that exposure to animal foods
may favor an intestinal environment
which could trigger systemic
inflammation and insulin resistance
dependent metabolic disorder such as
type 2 diabetes
and it's the reduced levels of
inflammation that may be the key factor
linking a plant-based gut microbiota
with protective health benefits
yeah but can't meat-eaters eat lots of
plants too
omnivores have constraints on diet
dependent gut microbiome metabolite
production in other words
it's the flip side of the vegan eating a
steak they can eat all the fiber they
want but may be lacking in fiber
munching machinery
at low levels of fiber intake the more
you eat the more of the beneficial short
chain fatty acids are made but at a
certain point your available fiber
feeders are maxed out there's only so
much you can benefit but those
habitually eating a plant-based diet
have been cultivating the growth of
these fiber feeders and the sky's the
limit unless of course you're eating
vegan junk
but whole food plant-based diets should
be effective in promoting a diverse
ecosystem of beneficial bacteria to
support both our gut microbiome and our
overall health
[Music]
you